<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<status id="status">
<p><emph>This section describes the status of this document at the
time of its publication. Other documents may supersede this document.
A list of current W3C publications and the latest revision of this
technical report can be found in the <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/TR/">W3C technical reports index</loc> at
http://www.w3.org/TR/.</emph></p>

<p>This document, published on &draft.day; &draft.month; &draft.year;, 
is a <loc href="http://www.w3.org/2005/10/Process-20051014/tr.html#ProposedEditedRec">Proposed Edited Recommendation</loc>
of the W3C. This second edition is not a new version of this specification;
its purpose is to clarify a number of issues that have become apparent since the
first edition was published.</p>

<p>This document has been produced by the <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/AudioVideo/TT/">Timed Text (TT) Working Group</loc> as
part of the W3C <loc href="http://www.w3.org/2008/WebVideo/">Video
in the Web Activity</loc>, following the procedures set out for the W3C <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Process/">Process</loc>.  The authors of this
document are listed in the header of this document, including input and review
by liaisons from the <loc href="http://www3.ebu.ch/cms/en/home">European
Broadcasting Union (EBU)</loc>, and the <loc href="https://www.smpte.org">Society
of Motion Picture &amp; Television Engineers (SMPTE)</loc>.</p>

<p>Publication as a Proposed Edited Recommendation does not imply endorsement by
the W3C Membership. This is a draft document and may be updated,
replaced or obsoleted by other documents at any time. It is
inappropriate to cite this document as other than work in progress.</p>

<p>W3C Advisory Committee Members are invited to send formal review comments
on this Proposed Edited Recommendation to the W3C Team until &review.end.date;.
Members of the W3C Advisory Committee will find the appropriate review form
for this document by consulting their
<loc href="http://www.w3.org/2002/09/wbs/myQuestionnaires">list
of WBS questionnaires</loc>.</p>

<p>This document incorporates changes made against the
<loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2010/REC-ttaf1-dfxp-20101118/">Recommendation</loc>
of 18 November 2010 that resolve all errata known at the date of publication.
A list of the errata that have been applied is provided in
<loc  href="https://dvcs.w3.org/hg/ttml/raw-file/default/ttml10/spec/ttml-changes.html#change-history-rec-to-2e-per">Changes
from Recommendation to Proposed Edited Recommendation (2nd Ed.)</loc>.</p>

<p>Please report errors in and submit comments on this document to the
W3C Timed Text public comments mailing list,
<loc href="mailto:public-tt-comments@w3.org">public-tt-comments@w3.org</loc>.
Please include the string <code>[ttml10se]</code> at the beginning of the
subject line of your report. Each email message should contain only one
error report. Archives of the comments and responses are available at
<loc href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-tt-comments/">http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-tt-comments/</loc>.</p>

<p>An updated <loc href="http://www.w3.org/2009/05/dfxp-results.html">implementation
report</loc>  will be made available, but the decision of the Director to transition
this document to Proposed Edited Recommendation did not depend on the existence of that
report.</p>

<p>The Timed Text Working Group plans to submit this specification for
consideration as a W3C Recommendation (Second Edition) as soon as the Working
Group has responded formally to all issues raised during the PER review period
against this document.</p>

<p>This document was produced by a group operating under the <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/">5 February
2004 W3C Patent Policy</loc>. W3C maintains a <loc role="disclosure"
href="http://www.w3.org/2004/01/pp-impl/34314/status#disclosures">public list of any patent
disclosures</loc> made in connection with the deliverables of the group;
that page also includes instructions for disclosing a patent. An
individual who has actual knowledge of a patent which the individual
believes contains <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/#def-essential">Essential
Claim(s)</loc> must disclose the information in accordance with <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/#sec-Disclosure">section
6 of the W3C Patent Policy</loc>.</p>

</status>
