<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE spec SYSTEM "xmlspec-tt-f.dtd" [
<!ENTITY draft.month.name "April">
<!ENTITY draft.month "04">
<!ENTITY draft.day "27">
<!ENTITY draft.year "2006">
<!ENTITY versionOfTT "1.0">
<!ENTITY doc.designation.nodate "ttaf1-req">
<!ENTITY doc.status "Working Group Note">
<!ENTITY doc.status.abbr "WD">
<!ENTITY doc.base.uri.root "/TR">
<!ENTITY doc.base.uri.noyear "http://www.w3.org&doc.base.uri.root;/">
<!ENTITY doc.base.uri "&doc.base.uri.noyear;&draft.year;/">
<!ENTITY doc.audience "internal review and discussion">
<!ENTITY doc.distribution "may be distributed freely, as long as
all text and legal notices remain intact">
<!ENTITY iso6.doc.date "&draft.year;&draft.month;&draft.day;">
<!ENTITY doc.designation.nostatus "&doc.designation.nodate;-&iso6.doc.date;">
<!ENTITY doc.designation.full "&doc.status.abbr;-&doc.designation.nostatus;">
<!ENTITY doc.designation "&doc.designation.full;">
<!ENTITY tbd "<phrase role='tbd'>To Be Defined</phrase>">
<!ENTITY aring "&#x00e5;">
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#x00e7;">
<!ENTITY nbsp "&#x00a0;">
<!ENTITY ndash "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY hArr "&#x21d4;">
<!ENTITY trade "&#x2122;">
<!ENTITY uuml "&#x00fc;">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="ttaf1-req.xsl"?>
<spec w3c-doctype="wg-note">
<header>
<title>Timed Text (TT) Authoring Format &versionOfTT; Use Cases and Requirements</title>
<w3c-designation>&doc.designation;</w3c-designation>
<w3c-doctype>W3C &doc.status;</w3c-doctype>
<pubdate>
<day>&draft.day;</day>
<month>&draft.month.name;</month>
<year>&draft.year;</year>
</pubdate>
<publoc>
<loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2006/NOTE-ttaf1-req-20060427/">http://www.w3.org/TR/2006/NOTE-ttaf1-req-20060427/</loc>
</publoc>
<latestloc>
<loc href="&doc.base.uri.noyear;&doc.designation.nodate;/">&doc.base.uri.noyear;&doc.designation.nodate;/</loc>
</latestloc>
<prevlocs>
<loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2003/WD-ttaf1-req-20030515/">http://www.w3.org/TR/2003/WD-ttaf1-req-20030515/</loc>
</prevlocs>
<authlist>
<author>
<name>Glenn Adams</name>
<affiliation>Extensible Formatting Systems, Inc.</affiliation>
<email href="mailto:glenn@xfsi.com">glenn@xfsi.com</email>
</author>
</authlist>
<abstract id="abstract">
<p>This document specifies usage scenarios and requirements for a timed text authoring
format. A timed text authoring format is a content type that represents timed text
media for the purpose of interchange among authoring systems.
Timed text is textual information that is intrinsically or extrinsically
associated with timing information.</p>
</abstract>
<status id="status">
<p><emph>This section describes the status of this document at the
time of its publication. Other documents may supersede this document.
A list of current W3C publications and the latest revision of this
technical report can be found in the <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/TR/">W3C technical reports index</loc> at
http://www.w3.org/TR/.</emph></p>
<p>This Working Group Note is the third publication of 
the Timed Text (TT)
Authoring Format &versionOfTT; Use Cases and
Requirements, and represents an editorial revision from the previous
version in order to transition from Working Draft to Working Group
Note.
This document has been produced by the <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/AudioVideo/TT/">Timed Text Working
Group</loc> as part of the W3C <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/AudioVideo/Activity">Synchronized Multimedia
Activity</loc>.
The authors of this document are the TT Working Group members, who
consider this document to be stable, and do not expect further
revision.
</p>
<p>Comments on this document should be sent to the email list <loc
href="mailto:public-tt@w3.org">public-tt@w3.org</loc>, which is the
public mailing list of Timed Text Working Group (<loc
href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-tt/">list
archives</loc>).
To subscribe, send an email to <loc
href="mailto:public-tt-request@w3.org">public-tt-request@w3.org</loc>
with the word <code>subscribe</code> in the subject line.</p>
<p>Publication as a Working Group Note does not imply endorsement
by the W3C Membership. This is a draft document and may be updated,
replaced or obsoleted by other documents at any time. It is
inappropriate to cite this document as other than work in
progress.</p>
<p>As of this publication, the Working Group does not expect this
document to become a W3C Recommendation, and therefore it has no
associated
<loc href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/">W3C
Patent Policy</loc> licensing obligations. If this
expectation changes, the Working Group will have an opportunity to
fulfill the associated patent policy requirements with respect to a future draft.</p>
</status>
<langusage><language id="en">English</language></langusage>
<revisiondesc><p>$Id$</p></revisiondesc>
</header>
<body>
<div1 id="intro">
<head>Introduction</head>
<p>This document specifies usage scenarios and requirements for a timed text authoring
format. A timed text authoring format is a content type that represents timed text
media for the purpose of interchange among authoring systems.
Timed text is textual information that is intrinsically or extrinsically
associated with timing information.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>This document incorporates requirements regarding stylistic
and timing functionality that range from simple to relatively complex. It is expected
that the use of this functionality will be partitioned into one or more profiles
represented by document types of increasing complexity. It is not expected that every
authoring system or ultimate consumer of timed text content will support all of this
functionality.</p>
</note>
<div2 id="motivation">
<head>Motivation</head>
<p>A principal motivation for the development of a common authoring format for
timed text is the lack of a standard content format that supports the representation
and interchange of textual information which is synchronized with other media
elements or which serves as a synchronization master itself.</p>
<p>Popular proprietary multimedia systems and their corresponding player
components have defined distinct timed text formats for each proprietary use. As
a consequence there is no common authoring format that serves as a
portable interchange format between such systems. A goal of the present work is
to define such a portable interchange format to ease the burden of authoring tool
developers and users as well as enhance portability of timed text content.</p>
<p>A side effect of the development and deployment of a common timed text authoring
format is that it simplifies the creation and distribution of synchronized text
for use with a multitude of devices, such as multimedia players, caption, subtitle,
and teletext encoders and decoders, character generators, LED displays, and other
text display devices.</p>
</div2>
<div2 id="model">
<head>System Model</head>
<p>The uses cases and requirements specified in this document are based upon a system
model, depicted in <specref ref="model-graphic"/>, wherein the timed text authoring format
serves as a bidirectional interchange format among a heterogeneous collection of
authoring systems, and as a unidirectional interchange format to a
heterogeneous collection of distribution formats after undergoing transcoding
to the target distribution formats as required.</p>
<table id="model-graphic" role="graphic">
<caption>Figure 1 &ndash; System Model</caption>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><graphic id="graphic-model" source="./images/model.png" alt="System Model"/></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<note role="explanation">
<p>In the figure depicted above, the acronym <emph>DFXP</emph> refers
to a profile of the timed text authoring format known as the Distribution
Format Exchange Profile, which is intended primarily to satisfy
interchange among existing legacy formats, and which may also be
distributed directly.</p>
</note>
<note role="explanation">
<p>This system model does not preclude the timed text authoring format from
being used as a distribution format in its own right.</p>
</note>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 id="definitions">
<head>Definitions</head>
<div2 id="acronyms">
<head>Acronyms</head>
<glist role="acronyms">
<gitem>
<label>TT</label>
<def>
<p>Timed Text</p>
</def>
</gitem>
<gitem>
<label>TT AS</label>
<def>
<p>Timed Text Authoring System</p>
</def>
</gitem>
<gitem>
<label>TT AF</label>
<def>
<p>Timed Text Authoring Format</p>
</def>
</gitem>
<gitem>
<label>TT WG</label>
<def>
<p>Timed Text Working Group</p>
</def>
</gitem>
</glist>
</div2>
<div2 id="terms">
<head>Terminology</head>
<glist>
<gitem>
<label>Timed Text</label>
<def>
<p>Textual information that is intrinsically or extrinsically
associated with timing information.</p>
</def>
</gitem>
<gitem>
<label>Timed Text Authoring Format</label>
<def>
<p>A content type that represents timed text media for the purpose
of interchange among authoring systems.</p>
</def>
</gitem>
<gitem>
<label>Timed Text Authoring System</label>
<def>
<p>A content authoring system capable of
importing and exporting timed text authoring format content.</p>
</def>
</gitem>
</glist>
</div2>
<div2 id="notations">
<head>Notations</head>
<p>The following notations are employed in this document:</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p><phrase role="strong">SXXX</phrase> &ndash; use case scenario <emph>XXX</emph></p>
</item>
<item>
<p><phrase role="strong">RXXX</phrase> &ndash; requirement <emph>XXX</emph></p>
</item>
<item>
<p><phrase role="strong">RX9X</phrase> &ndash; solution space requirement <emph>X9X</emph></p>
</item>
<item>
<p><phrase role="strong">NXXX</phrase> &ndash; non-requirement <emph>XXX</emph></p>
</item>
</ulist>
</div2>
</div1>
<div1 id="scenarios">
<head>Use Case Scenarios</head>
<uselist id="S0XX">
<useitem id="S000" type="simple">
<head>Captioning Audio</head>
<use>
<p>A caption service provider needs a common content authoring format by means of which
a textual expression of audio information may be associated with such audio
information in a time synchronized manner.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>In the context of captioning an aggregate audio/video service, both audio and
caption information are typically synchronized to the video track as the
timebase master.</p>
</note>
</use>
</useitem>
<useitem id="S001" type="simple">
<head>Subtitling Audio</head>
<use>
<p>A subtitle service provider needs a common content authoring format by means of which
a textual expression of the original or a translation of the original natural language
(speech) audio information may be associated with such audio information in a time
synchronized manner.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>In the context of subtitling an aggregate audio/video service, both audio and
subtitle information are typically synchronized to the video track as the
timebase master.</p>
</note>
<note role="explanation">
<p>The distinction between <emph>captioning</emph> and <emph>subtitling</emph> is best
expressed as follows: captioning is expressly intended to serve the needs of deaf and
hard of hearing users, and typically contains transcriptions of speech and non-speech audio information;
in contrast, subtitling is generally intended to serve the needs of hearing users who
don't have access to an audio track (e.g., in muting situations) or don't understand
the natural language of the speech contained in the audio track. Subtitling is often
viewed as a paraphrase or a translation of speech information, as opposed to a transcription of
all audio information.</p>
<p>In the absence of captioning information, subtitling information may also be
used by deaf and hard of hearing
users, provided that it is available in the original natural language.</p>
</note>
<note role="explanation">
<p>Some user communities use the term <emph>subtitling</emph> to encompass both captioning
and subtitling uses as distinguished in the previous note.</p>
</note>
</use>
</useitem>
<useitem id="S002" type="simple">
<head>Description</head>
<use>
<p>A description service provider needs a common content authoring format in which
a textual description of video information or a textual expression of an
audio description of video information may be associated with such video
information in a time synchronized manner.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>When a description is rendered by an audio track, such a description is commonly
referred to as an <emph>Audio Description</emph>.</p>
</note>
<note role="explanation">
<p>In the use of aural forms of visual description, it may be the case that
the duration of an aural form of a description exceeds the duration
of the visual information being described. In a presentation device, this
necessitates manual or automatic pausing of the video track in order to
fully render the aural form of description. It is likely that similar
modes of presentation will be required for timed text representations of
video descriptions.</p>
</note>
<note role="explanation">
<p>This use case scenario is not intended to serve as a general form of <emph>metadata</emph>
description of related video or audio content.</p>
</note>
</use>
</useitem>
<useitem id="S003" type="simple">
<head>Generic Timed Text</head>
<use>
<p>A generic timed text service provider needs a common content authoring format in which
textual information can be presented in a time synchronized manner.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>In the context of using a generic timed text service, timed text information
serves as the timebase master, with which other possible timed media may
be associated.</p>
</note>
<note role="explanation">
<p>Examples of the use of generic timed text
include (but are not limited to):
marquee signs, timed text oriented presentations, scrolling text presentation, etc.</p>
</note>
</use>
</useitem>
</uselist>
</div1>
<div1 id="requirements">
<head>Requirements</head>
<div2 id="general">
<head>General</head>
<!-- general requirements list -->
<rlist id="R1xx">
<ritem id="R100" type="dreq">
<head>Specification Format</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF specification(s) shall be authored using XML and XSL Stylesheets
based on <bibref ref="xmlspec"/> and shall adhere to best current practices in the
W3C for specification style and quality assurance.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R101" type="dreq">
<head>Specification Modularity</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF specification(s) shall be defined in a modular manner that logically separates
significant areas of functionality to as great extent as is practical.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R102" type="dreq">
<head>Specification Organization</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF specification(s) shall be organized in such a manner as to
separate the following aspects:</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p>TT Framework</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>TT Core Vocabulary</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>TT Core Document Types</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>TT Extension Vocabulary(ies)</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>TT Extension Document Type(s)</p>
</item>
</ulist>
<p/>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R103" type="dreq">
<head>Core and Periphery</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF specification(s) shall be defined in such a manner that core functionality
is logically separated from peripheral functionality.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R104" type="dreq">
<head>Evolution of Core</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF specification(s) shall be defined in such a manner that core functionality
can evolve over time, e.g., by the specification of multiple levels (or versions)
of core functionality.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R105" type="dreq">
<head>Ownership of Core</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF specification(s) shall be defined in such a manner that core
functionality be specified soley by the TT WG or, in the event that the
TT WG is terminated, its successors within the W3C.</p>
<note role="assumption">
<p>It is assumed that one or more appropriate namespace mechanisms will be
used to segregate core functionality defined or adopted in the TT AF from
peripheral functionality defined or adopted by clients of the TT AF.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R106" type="dreq">
<head>Surjection of Core</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF specification(s) shall be defined in such a manner that for every
item in the TT AF core vocabulary, there shall be at least one TT AF core document
type that makes use of that item, i.e., there exists a surjection from the
set of TT AF core document types to the set of TT AF vocabulary items referenced
by those document types.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>The TT AF specification(s) may define standardized peripheral vocabulary that
is not referenced by any TT AF core document type.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R107" type="dreq">
<head>Evolution of Periphery</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF specification(s) shall be defined in such a manner that peripheral functionality
can evolve over time, e.g., by the future specification of one or more
peripheral functionality modules.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R108" type="dreq">
<head>Ownership of Periphery</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF specification(s) shall be defined in such a manner that peripheral functionality
need not be specified by the TT WG or the W3C, but may be specified by other
W3C WGs as well as non-W3C clients of the TT AF.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R109" type="freq">
<head>Transformability</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of being transformed, without undue complexity, into
one or more legacy timed text content formats, e.g., <bibref ref="threegpp"/>,
<bibref ref="qtext"/>, <bibref ref="realtext"/>, <bibref ref="sami"/>, etc.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>The above list of potential target timed text content formats is strictly
informative, and is not intended to be exhuastive.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R110" type="freq">
<head>Streamable Tranformation</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of being transformed into an idealized streamable
representation format.</p>
<note role="non-requirement">
<p>It is not required that an idealized streamable representation format be
defined by the TT AF specification(s); however, the definition of such a format
may be the subject of future activities by the TT WG.</p>
</note>
<note role="information">
<p>It is intended that existing closed captioning and subtitle streaming
formats used by analog and digital television services as well as timed text
used in the context of streaming audio and motion video formats be potentially
targeted by one or more transformations of the TT AF. These formats include
<bibref ref="eia608b"/>, <bibref ref="eia708b"/>, <bibref ref="en300706"/>,
<bibref ref="en300743"/>, etc.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R111" type="freq">
<head>Accessibility &ndash; Content</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall include the following accessibility related features:</p>
<ulist>
<item><p>Support for a mechanism to explicitly associate
<emph>Equivalent Alternatives</emph> to the textual information in
the TT presentation in accordance with <bibref ref="xmlaccess"/>
Guideline 1.</p></item>
<item><p>Support for <emph>Content Rendering Adaption</emph> in 
accordance with <bibref ref="smilaccess"/>, Section 5. See also
<specref ref="R207"/>.</p></item>
<item><p>Use of a default text vocabulary that satisfies guideline 2
of <bibref ref="xmlaccess"/> regarding structural and semantical
stringency.</p></item>
<item><p> Ability to extend or replace the default text vocabulary
with other XML dialects to represent the textual information of the
TT presentation. See also <specref ref="R205"/>.</p></item>
<item><p>Support for explicit definition of a <emph>Navigational
Structure</emph> associated with the TT presentation in accordance
with <bibref ref="smilaccess"/>, Section 4.3.</p></item>
</ulist>
<p/>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R112" type="freq">
<head>Accessibility &ndash; Authoring System</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF specification(s) shall be defined in such a manner as to require
a TT AS to adhere to all applicable aspects of <bibref ref="atag10"/>.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<!-- end of general requirements -->
</rlist>
</div2>
<div2 id="content">
<head>Content</head>
<!-- content requirements list -->
<rlist id="R2xx">
<ritem id="R200" type="freq">
<head>Authorability</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of being created and modified using a plain text
editor, e.g., emacs, vi, etc.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R201" type="freq">
<head>Multiple Natural Languages</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of representing content of different natural languages,
where the content of distinct languages may be segregated into separate document instances
or may be integrated into a single document instance.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R202" type="freq">
<head>Natural Language Coverage</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of representing content of at least those specific
natural languages that may be represented with <bibref ref="unicode32"/>.
</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R203" type="freq">
<head>Natural Language Association Granularity</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of associating natural language binding information
with plain text information at the granularity of a single coded character.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R204" type="freq">
<head>Minimum Character Representability</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of representing every coded character available in
<bibref ref="unicode32"/> by using only those characters in <bibref ref="ascii"/>.
</p>
<note role="use">
<p>This requirement facilitates the entry and editing of characters
in a TT AF document instance that would otherwise not be permitted due to lack of
an appropriate character input method or lack of support for a
non-ASCII character encoding system.</p>
<p>It is assumed that every TT AS will provide a means to enter and edit
TT AF document instances represented in the ASCII character set.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R205" type="freq">
<head>Intrinsic and Extrinsic Text Content</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing text content intrinsically within a TT AF
document instance, extrinsically by referencing from a TT AF document instance to text
content in one or more external resources, or in any combination of these two modes.
</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R206" type="freq">
<head>Markup Association</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of associating structural markup with intrinsic and
extrinsic text content, where such markup may denote either or both semantic (functional)
and presentational (formal) properties of the content.
</p>
<note>
<p>In this context, <emph>presentational</emph> properties designate both stylistic
and timing related presentation information.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R207" type="freq">
<head>Conditional Content</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing conditional content, where each alternative
content choice is governed by one or more test expressions such that exactly one or zero
content choice is selected when evaluating each choice in a predefined order.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R208" type="freq">
<head>Flowed Text</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing authorial intention to flow (layout) text
content in an idealized, but unspecified user agent.
</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>In this context, the concept of <emph>flow</emph> refers to an implied process by
means of which textual information expressed in the character domain is mapped
to a positioned glyph codomain.</p>
</note>
<note role="non-requirement">
<p>It is not required that an idealized user agent or behavior of such a user agent be
defined by the TT AF specification(s); however, the definition of such a user agent or
user agent behavior may be the subject of future activities by the TT WG.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R209" type="freq">
<head>Logical Flowed Text Vocabulary</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing the following vocabulary as pertains to
logical flowed text content:
</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p>body</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>division</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>paragraph</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>phrase</p>
</item>
</ulist>
<note role="explanation">
<p>A generic <emph>role</emph> attribute is expected to be provided for use with these
items in order to express distinct stylistic and semantic roles, e.g., a <emph>paragraph</emph>
role may be associated with a <emph>division</emph> item to indicate that the logical division
expressed corresponds to a stylistic and semantic paragraph.</p>
</note>
<note role="example">
<p>One possible mapping for this vocabulary is to <el>xhtml:body</el>,
<el>xhtml:div</el>, <el>xhtml:p</el>, and <el>xhtml:span</el>, respectively,
as defined by <bibref ref="xhtml1"/>.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R210" type="freq">
<head>Presentational Flowed Text Vocabulary</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing the following vocabulary as pertains to
presentational flowed text content:
</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p>block</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>block container</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>character</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>flow</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>forced line break</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>inline</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>inline container</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>region</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>viewport</p>
</item>
</ulist>
<note role="explanation">
<p>The items enumerated above are drawn in part from similarly named items
defined by <bibref ref="xsl"/>, Section 6, <emph>Formatting Objects</emph>.</p>
</note>
<note role="explanation">
<p>The <emph>forced line break</emph> item may be expressed in terms
of the <emph>character</emph> item, where the specified character has line separator or line
break semantics.</p>
<p>The use of this item in combination with a <emph>wrap option</emph>
style parameter with the value <code>nowrap</code> permits an intermediate mode
of text representation with formatting semantics that fall between flowed text
and non-flowed text.</p>
</note>
<note role="explanation">
<p>The <emph>viewport</emph> and <emph>region</emph> items are intended to be
analogous to the <bibref ref="xsl"/> vocabulary <code>fo:simple-page-master</code>
and <code>fo:region-*</code>, respectively.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R211" type="freq">
<head>Flowed Text Vocabulary Relationship</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be defined in such a manner that a default relationship
between logical and presentational flowed text vocabulary may be assumed as follows:</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p>body &hArr; flow</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>division (display: block) &hArr; block container</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>paragraph &hArr; block</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>division (display: inline) &hArr; inline container</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>phrase &hArr; inline</p>
</item>
</ulist>
<note role="explanation">
<p>Parsed character data (<code>#PCDATA</code>) that appears in
logical flowed text content should be assumed to map by default to
parsed character data or <emph>character</emph> in presentational flowed
text content.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R212" type="freq">
<head>Flowed Text Vocabulary Separation</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be defined in such a manner that use of logical flowed text
vocabulary is separated from use of presentational flowed text vocabulary.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>It is not required that the TT AF specification(s) define a document type
that supports the simultaneous use of both logical and presentational flowed text
vocabulary.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R213" type="freq">
<head>Non-Flowed Text</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing authorial intention to render non-flowed text
content in an idealized, but unspecified user agent.
</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>In this context, the concept of <emph>non-flowed text</emph> refers to textual
information that is explicitly associated with positioned glyph information at authoring
time; i.e., all bidirectional processing and character to glyph substitution processing
and glyph position assignment has already occurred.</p>
</note>
<note role="non-requirement">
<p>It is not required that an idealized user agent or behavior of such a user agent be
defined by the TT AF specification(s); however, the definition of such a user agent or
user agent behavior may be the subject of future activities by the TT WG.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R214" type="freq">
<head>Non-Flowed Text Vocabulary</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing the following vocabulary as pertains to
non-flowed text content:</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p>area</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>glyph</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>glyph sequence</p>
</item>
</ulist>
<note role="explanation">
<p>The glyph and glyph sequence vocabulary items are intended to make direct reference to
specific glyphs in specific fonts, having already been transformed from the character
domain to the glyph domain. References to glyphs would typically take the form of a glyph
identifier or a glyph code. For further information on character to the
glyph mapping process, see <bibref ref="charmod"/>, Section 3.1.3,
<emph>Units of Visual Rendering</emph>.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R215" type="freq">
<head>Hybrid Flowed and Non-Flowed Text</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing authorial intention to create a hybrid of
flowed and non-flowed text content; however, such an expression may require that these
two types of content be segregated at a specific level of granularity.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R216" type="freq">
<head>Hyperlinking</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing simple hyperlinks, where the ending
(destination) resource is either the starting (source) resource or an external resource.
</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R217" type="freq">
<head>Embedded Graphics</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing block and inline,
embedded graphics of both bitmap and vector or outline formats.
</p>
<p>If block or inline graphics are used for the purpose of expressing pre-rasterized
text in a bitmap format, then the original text that produced such a pre-rasterized form shall
also be required to be present in TT AF content.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R218" type="freq">
<head>Non-Embedded Graphics</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing block and inline,
non-embedded graphics of both bitmap and vector or outline formats, where a graphic is
represented by an external resource.
</p>
<p>If block or inline graphics are used for the purpose of expressing pre-rasterized
text in a bitmap format, then the original text that produced such a pre-rasterized form shall
also be required to be present in TT AF content.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R219" type="freq">
<head>Embedded Fonts</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing embedded fonts of both bitmap and
outline formats.
</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R220" type="freq">
<head>Non-Embedded Fonts</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing non-embedded fonts of both bitmap and
outline formats, where a font is represented by an external resource.
</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R221" type="freq">
<head>Descriptive Vocabulary</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of associating text content
with descriptive information from an appropriate domain of discourse.</p>
<p/>
<note role="explanation">
<p>See <bibref ref="tei"/>, Chapter 10, <emph>Base Tag Set for Drama</emph>,
and Chapter 11, <emph>Transcription of Speech</emph>, for examples of descriptive
vocabulary pertaining to drama and the transcription of speech, respectively.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R222" type="freq">
<head>Embedded Audio</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing embedded audio that is intended to be played or
rendered in sequence or in parallel with associated text content.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>The use of embedded audio is intended to support aural cues that may accompany text.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R223" type="freq">
<head>Non-Embedded Audio</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing non-embedded audio that is intended to be played or
rendered in sequence or in parallel with associated text content, where the audio
content is represented by an external resource.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>The use of non-embedded audio is intended to support aural cues that may accompany text.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R290" type="sreq">
<head>Markup Format</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall support the use of both <bibref ref="xml10"/> and
<bibref ref="xml11"/> as serialized forms of a TT AF XML information set.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>See <bibref ref="infoset"/> for further information on an <emph>XML
information set</emph>.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R291" type="sreq">
<head>Markup Format and Unicode Interaction</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall require or recommend adherence to the practices
recommended by <bibref ref="uxml"/>.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R292" type="sreq">
<head>Extrinsic Resource References</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall support the use of <bibref ref="xlink"/> for the purpose of
referencing external resources.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R293" type="dreq">
<head>Schema Validity Specification</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF specification(s) shall be defined in such a manner that the normative validity of
markup content be specified in terms of either or both
<bibref ref="rng"/> and <bibref ref="xsd-1"/> in combination with <bibref ref="xsd-2"/>.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<!-- end of content requirements -->
</rlist>
</div2>
<div2 id="styling">
<head>Styling</head>
<!-- styling requirements list -->
<rlist id="R3xx">
<ritem id="R300" type="freq">
<head>Inline Styling</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of inline styling, where inline
styling means the inclusion of stylistic presentation information in a TT AF
document instance.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R301" type="freq">
<head>Inline Styling Form</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of specifying inline styling by means of (1) distinct
attributes, (2) a generic attribute, e.g., <code>style</code>, and (3) one or more
inline stylesheets.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R302" type="freq">
<head>Out-of-Line Styling</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of out-of-line styling, where out-of-line styling
means the association of stylistic presentation information with TT AF content
via some mechanism external to a TT AF document instance.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R303" type="freq">
<head>Out-Of-Line Styling Form</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of specifying out-of-line styling by means of one or
more external stylesheets.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R304" type="freq">
<head>Styling Prioritization</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of associating priorities with stylistic presentation
information in order to permit the resolution of multiple style specifications that
apply to the same content.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R305" type="freq">
<head>Style Parameters &ndash; Aural</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of associating the following aural style
parameters with timed text content:</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p>azimuth</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>cue before, during, after</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>elevation</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>pause before, after</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>pitch</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>pitch range</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>richness</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>speaking mode</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>speech rate</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>stress</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>voice family</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>volume</p>
</item>
</ulist>
<note role="explanation">
<p>For further information on these style parameters, see <bibref ref="xsl"/>,
Section 7.6, <emph>Common Aural Properties</emph> and <bibref ref="css2"/>.</p>
</note>
<note role="explanation">
<p>For further information on the <emph>speaking mode</emph> aural style parameter,
see discussion of <code>speak</code>, <code>speak-numeral</code>, and
<code>speak-punctuation</code> properties described in
<bibref ref="xsl"/>, Section 7.6.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R306" type="freq">
<head>Style Parameters &ndash; Visual</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of associating the following visual style
parameters with timed text content:</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p>absolute position</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>background color</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>baseline alignment point</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>baseline alignment</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>baseline dominance</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>baseline shift</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>bidirectional treatment</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>block progression dimension</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>block scroll amount</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>border before, after, start, end</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>break before, after</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>clear</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>color</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>color profile name</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>display none, block, inline</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>display alignment</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>float</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>font family</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>font size</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>font style</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>font weight</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>height</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>indent start, end</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>inline progression dimension</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>inline scroll amount</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>intrusion-displace</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>line feed treatment</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>line height</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>line stacking strategy</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>line wrapping option</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>opacity</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>origin (top, left)</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>overflow</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>padding before, after, start, end</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>reference orientation</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>relative position</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>space before, after, start, end</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>text alignment</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>text altitude (ascent)</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>text decoration</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>text depth (descent)</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>text indent (first line)</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>text shadow</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>visibility</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>white space collapse</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>white space treatment</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>width</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>writing mode</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>z-index</p>
</item>
</ulist>
<note role="explanation">
<p>For further information on these style parameters, see <bibref ref="xsl"/>,
Section 7, <emph>Formatting Properties</emph> and <bibref ref="css2"/>.</p>
</note>
<note role="explanation">
<p>The style parameters <emph>break before</emph> and <emph>break after</emph> are
intended to model the like named style properties defined by <bibref ref="xsl"/>,
Section 7.19, <emph>Keeps and Breaks Properties</emph>, except that the possible values of these
parameters are expected to be restricted to <code>auto</code>, <code>line</code>, and <code>inherit</code>.
The new value <code>line</code> is intended to denote a line area context in order to express
that a line break should precede or follow the element associated with this parameter.</p>
<p>Unlike XSL, these parameters apply only to inline vocabulary, and not block vocabulary.</p>
</note>
<note role="explanation">
<p>A <emph>style parameter</emph> is intended to convey the notion of any type
of style specification or declaration whether it is expressed as an attribute or a property.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R307" type="freq">
<head>Style Parameters &ndash; Visual &ndash; Temporal Fill Mode</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF may be capable of associating the following visual style
parameters that pertain to temporal filling (flowing) of timed text content:</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p>temporal fill mode</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>temporal fill direction</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>temporal block clear mode</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>temporal fill interval</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>temporal inter-fill interval</p>
</item>
</ulist>
<note role="explanation">
<p>These parameters are intended to permit the expression of authorial intent with respect
to the temporal filling (stacking) of glyph areas within a line area and line areas within a block area.</p>
<p>The <emph>temporal fill mode</emph> parameter permits specifying the granularity of temporal
filling, e.g., line, word, character. The <emph>temporal fill direction</emph> parameter permits specifying
the direction of fill (stacking) independently from the writing mode. The <emph>temporal block clear
mode</emph> parameter permits specifying whether the containing block is cleared or is automatically
scrolled, and by what extent, when the block is filled. The <emph>temporal fill interval</emph>
parameter permits specifying the interval that a filled area should remain static before processing the next fill.
The <emph>temporal inter-fill interval</emph> parameter permits specifying the interval
between the end of a prior fill interval and the start of a subsequent fill interval.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R390" type="sreq">
<head>Style Parameter Symmetry</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be defined in such a manner that if a stylistic presentation
parameter may be specified as a style property, then that parameter shall also be
specifiable as a style attribute, and vice-versa.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>In this context, a style <emph>attribute</emph> refers to an attribute expressed
in a markup language (e.g., an XML attribute), while a style <emph>property</emph>
refers to a property expressed in a style language (e.g., a CSS property).</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R391" type="dreq">
<head>Style Parameter Definitions</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be defined in such a manner that if there is a conflict
when adopting the name or value semantics of a style parameter specification,
then the following order shall hold for resolving such a conflict:</p>
<olist>
<item>
<p>XSL FO</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>SVG</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>SMIL</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>CSS Level 2</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>CSS Level 3</p>
</item>
</olist>
<p/>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R392" type="dreq">
<head>Style Element Type Shorthand Equivalence</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be defined in such a manner that to the extent that
stylistic oriented markup element types are defined or adopted, then such element
types shall be defined as shorthand equivalents of non-stylistic oriented
element types in combination with specific style parameters.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<!-- end of styling requirements -->
</rlist>
</div2>
<div2 id="timing">
<head>Timing</head>
<!-- timing requirements list -->
<rlist id="R4xx">
<ritem id="R401" type="freq">
<head>Inline Timing</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of inline timing, where inline
timing means the inclusion of temporal presentation markup in a TT AF
document instance.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R402" type="freq">
<head>Out-of-Line Timing</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of out-of-line timing, where out-of-line timing
means the association of temporal presentation information with TT AF content
via some mechanism external to a TT AF document instance.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R403" type="freq">
<head>Synchronization Parameters</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing the following
synchronization parameters in terms of any legal combination that
expresses a possibly repeated or restarted,
single, simple interval:</p>
<ulist>
<item><p>begin</p></item>
<item><p>dur</p></item>
<item><p>end</p></item>
<item><p>endsync</p></item>
<item><p>fill</p></item>
<item><p>fillDefault</p></item>
<item><p>repeatCount</p></item>
<item><p>repeatDur</p></item>
<item><p>restart</p></item>
<item><p>restartDefault</p></item>
</ulist>
<note role="explanation">
<p>For further information on these synchronization parameters, see <bibref ref="smil20"/>,
Section 10, <emph>The SMIL 2.0 Timing and Synchronization Module</emph>.</p>
</note>
<note role="non-requirement">
<p>It is not required that the TT AF support the specification of multiple
simple intervals, i.e., multiple start, duration, or begin values.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R404" type="freq">
<head>Synchronization Parameter Value Space Semantics</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing the following synchronization parameter
value space semantics:</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p><emph>Offset Values</emph> &nbsp;&ndash; a clock offset from an implied or
explicit synchronization timebase;</p>
</item>
<item>
<p><emph>Event Values</emph> &nbsp;&ndash; a clock offset from a named event associated
with an implied or explicit element node, including, at a minimum, named events
that indicate the beginning or end of a timed element's active interval;</p>
</item>
<item>
<p><emph>Access Key Values</emph> &nbsp;&ndash; a clock offset from a specific key press
event;</p>
</item>
<item>
<p><emph>Media Marker Values</emph> &nbsp;&ndash; a clock offset from a media marker,
including, at a minimum, a media marker that denotes a SMPTE time code;</p>
</item>
<item>
<p><emph>Wallclock Values</emph> &nbsp;&ndash; a clock offset from an absolute
wallclock time in an implied or explicit time zone.</p>
</item>
</ulist>
<note role="non-requirement">
<p>It is not required that the TT AF support the specification of negative
offset values.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R405" type="freq">
<head>Time Containment Semantics</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing sequential, parallel, and
exclusive time containment semantics of consituent timed text content.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>For further information on these time containment semantics, see <bibref ref="smil20"/>,
Section 10, <emph>The SMIL 2.0 Timing and Syncrhonization Module</emph>.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<!-- end of timing requirements -->
</rlist>
</div2>
<div2 id="animation">
<head>Animation</head>
<rlist id="R5XX">
<ritem id="R500" type="freq">
<head>Animation Modes</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing animation according to the following modes:</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p>continuous &ndash; linear</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>continuous &ndash; non-linear</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>discrete</p>
</item>
</ulist>
<note role="explanation">
<p>By <emph>animation</emph> is meant the ability to alter some parameter or value over
time.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R501" type="freq">
<head>Scroll Animation</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing animated scrolling of content, both
in block and inline progression directions, with independent expression of
scroll in, scroll out, and scroll repetition.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R502" type="freq">
<head>Highlight Animation</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing animated highlighting of content, with
granularity at the level of individual characters or glyphs.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R503" type="freq">
<head>Fade Transition Animation</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing animated fade transitions of content, with
granularity at the level of individual regions or areas.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>See <specref ref="R210"/> and <specref ref="R214"/> for information on <emph>region</emph>
and <emph>area</emph> vocabulary items, respectively.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R504" type="freq">
<head>Animated Style Parameters &ndash; Aural</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of animating the following aural style parameters:</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p>azimuth</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>elevation</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>speaking mode</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>speech rate</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>volume</p>
</item>
</ulist>
<p/>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R505" type="freq">
<head>Animated Style Parameters &ndash; Visual</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of animating the following visual style parameters:</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p>background color</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>block scroll amount</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>border color</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>color</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>display</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>inline scroll amount</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>opacity</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>origin</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>visibility</p>
</item>
</ulist>
<note role="explanation">
<p>It is possible to express fade-in and fade-out transitions by means of
animating the <emph>opacity</emph> style parameter.</p>
</note>
<note role="explanation">
<p>Animation of the <emph>display</emph> style parameter may cause reflow (reformatting)
of content in a user agent at each animation step.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="N506" type="nreq">
<head>Animated Content</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF is not required to support the animation of content.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>By <emph>animation of content</emph> is meant the dynamic addition or changing
of element content by means of animation functionality, e.g., replacing the text
content of an element.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
</rlist>
</div2>
<div2 id="metadata">
<head>Metadata</head>
<rlist id="R6XX">
<ritem id="R600" type="freq">
<head>Metadata Item Association</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of associating arbitrary metadata, expressed as
<emph>metadata items</emph>, with (1) a TT AF document instance and (2) any
element contained within a TT AF document instance.</p>
<note role="non-requirement">
<p>It is not required that metadata be able to be associated with an element's
attributes or with any other child of an element other than a child that is
characterized as an element itself.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R601" type="freq">
<head>Metadata Item Constituents</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing the following constituents of individual
metadata items:</p>
<ulist>
<item>
<p>name</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>value type</p>
</item>
<item>
<p>value</p>
</item>
</ulist>
<p/>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R602" type="freq">
<head>Metadata Item Value Representation</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall give preference to the representation of metadata item values
as element content as opposed to attribute content.</p>
<note role="explanation">
<p>By <emph>element content</emph> is meant those children of
an element information item that are characterized as elements or as character data.
By <emph>attribute content</emph> is meant the normalized values of the
attributes of an element information item.</p>
</note>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R603" type="freq">
<head>Metadata Item Extensibility</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF shall be capable of expressing metadata items whose names, value
types, and semantics are defined externally to the TT AF specification(s).</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R604" type="freq">
<head>Metadata Item Validation</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF specification(s) shall be defined in such a manner as to permit
and potentially require the ability to validate metadata.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
<ritem id="R690" type="sreq">
<head>Dublin Core Preference</head>
<req>
<p>The TT AF specification(s) shall be defined in such a manner as to give
preference to those metadata items defined by <bibref ref="dcmes"/> in
case that a conflict exists with another candidate metadata representation.</p>
</req>
</ritem>
</rlist>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
<back>
<div1 id="references">
<head>References</head>
<blist>
<bibl id="ascii" key="ASCII (ANSI X3.4)">
American National Standards Institute.
<titleref>ANSI X3.4: Coded character set &ndash; 7-bit American national code for
information interchange</titleref>. New York, 1986.
</bibl>
<bibl id="atag10" key="ATAG 1.0">Jutta Treviranus, Charles McCathieNevile, Ian Jacobs, Jan Richards, Eds.,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/ATAG10/">Authoring Tool Accessibility Guidelines 1.0</titleref>, W3C Recommendation, 3 February 2000. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/ATAG10/">http://www.w3.org/TR/ATAG10/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="dcmes" key="DCMES 1.1">Dublin Core Metadata Initiative,
<titleref href="http://dublincore.org/documents/dces/">Dublin Core Metadata Element Set, Version 1.1: Reference Description</titleref>. (See
<xspecref href="http://dublincore.org/documents/dces/">http://dublincore.org/documents/dces/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="rng" key="RELAX NG">James Clark and Makato Murata, Eds.,
<titleref href="http://www.relaxng.org/spec-20011203.html">RELAX NG Specification</titleref>, OASIS Committee Specification, 3 December 2001. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.relaxng.org/spec-20011203.html">http://www.relaxng.org/spec-20011203.html</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="unicode32" key="Unicode 3.2">The Unicode Consortium,
<titleref>The Unicode Standard, Version 3.2.0</titleref> is defined by <titleref>The Unicode Standard, Version 3.0</titleref>
(Reading, MA, Addison-Wesley, 2000. ISBN 0-201-61633-5), as amended by the <titleref>Unicode Standard Annex #27: Unicode 3.1</titleref>
(see <loc href="http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr27/">http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr27</loc>)
and by the <titleref>Unicode Standard Annex #28: Unicode 3.2</titleref>
(see <loc href="http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr28/">http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr28</loc>).
</bibl>
<bibl id="uxml" key="Unicode in XML">Martin J. D&uuml;rst and
Asums Freytag,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/unicode-xml/">Unicode in XML and other Markup Languages</titleref>,
W3C Note. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/unicode-xml/">http://www.w3.org/TR/unicode-xml/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="smilaccess" key="WAI SMIL AG">Marja-Riitta Koivunen,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SMIL-access/">Accessibility Features of SMIL</titleref>, W3C Note, 21 September 1999. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/SMIL-access/">http://www.w3.org/TR/SMIL-access/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="xmlaccess" key="WAI XML AG">Daniel Dardailler, Sean B. Palmer, Charles McCathieNevile, Eds.,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xag.html">XML Accessibility Guidelines</titleref>, W3C Working Draft, 3 October 2002. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xag.html">http://www.w3.org/TR/xag.html</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="xlink" key="XLink">Steve DeRose, Eve Maler, David Orchard, Eds.,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">XML Linking Language (XLink) Version 1.0</titleref>,
W3C Recommendation. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/">http://www.w3.org/TR/xlink/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="xml10" key="XML 1.0">Tim Bray, Jean Paoli, C. M.
Sperberg-McQueen, Eve Maler, Eds.,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml">Extensible Markup Language (XML)
1.0 (Second Edition)</titleref>, W3C Recommendation. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml">http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="xml11" key="XML 1.1">John Cowan,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2002/CR-xml11-20021015/">Extensible Markup Language (XML)
1.1</titleref>, W3C Candidate Recommendation, 15 October 2002. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2002/CR-xml11-20021015/">http://www.w3.org/TR/2002/CR-xml11-20021015/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="infoset" key="XML InfoSet">John Cowan and Richard Tobin,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml-infoset/">XML Information Set</titleref>,
W3C Recommendation, 24 Oct 2001. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml-infoset/">http://www.w3.org/TR/xml-infoset/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="xsd-1" key="XML Schema Part 1">Henry S. Thompson, David Beech,
Murray Maloney, Noah Mendelsohn, Eds.,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-1/">XML Schema Part 1: Structures</titleref>,
W3C Recommendation. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-1/">http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-1/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="xsd-2" key="XML Schema Part 2">Paul Biron and Ashok Malhotra,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/">XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes</titleref>,
W3C Recommendation. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/">http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="xmlspec" key="XML Spec">Norman Walsh,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/2002/xmlspec/">The XML Spec Schema and Stylesheets</titleref>,
W3C. (See <loc href="http://www.w3.org/2002/xmlspec/">http://www.w3.org/2002/xmlspec/</loc>).
</bibl>
</blist>
</div1>
<inform-div1 id="other-references">
<head>Other References</head>
<blist>
<bibl id="threegpp" key="3GPP">3rd Generation Partnership Project,
<titleref href="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/26234.htm">Technical Specification
Group Services and System Aspects; Transparent End-To-End Packet-Switched Streaming Service (PSS);
Protocols and Codecs</titleref>, 3GPP Organizational Partners. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/26234.htm">http://www.3gpp.org/ftp/Specs/html-info/26234.htm</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="charmod" key="CharMod">Martin J. D&uuml;rst et al., Eds.,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/charmod/">Character Model for the World Wide Web 1.0: Fundamentals</titleref>,
W3C Recommendation, 15 February 2005. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/charmod/">http://www.w3.org/TR/charmod/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="css2" key="CSS Level 2">Bert Bos, H&aring;kon Wium Lie, Chris Lilley,
Ian Jacobs, Eds.,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-CSS2/">Cascading Style Sheets, Level 2</titleref>,
W3C Recommendation. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-CSS2/">http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-CSS2/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="dcmi-terms" key="DCMI Terms">Dublin Core Metadata Initiative,
<titleref href="http://dublincore.org/documents/2003/03/04/dcmi-terms/">DCMI Metadata Terms</titleref>. (See
<xspecref href="http://dublincore.org/documents/2003/03/04/dcmi-terms/">http://dublincore.org/documents/2003/03/04/dcmi-terms/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="eia608b" key="EIA-608B">Electronics Industry Alliance (EIA),
<titleref href="http://www.ce.org/standards/standard_details.asp?id=270">Line 21 Data Services</titleref>. (See 
<xspecref href="http://www.ce.org/standards/standard_details.asp?id=270">http://www.ce.org/standards/standard_details.asp?id=270</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="eia708b" key="EIA-708B">Electronics Industry Alliance (EIA),
<titleref href="http://www.ce.org/standards/standard_details.asp?id=249">Digital Television (DTV) Closed Captioning</titleref>. (See 
<xspecref href="http://www.ce.org/standards/standard_details.asp?id=249">http://www.ce.org/standards/standard_details.asp?id=249</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="en300706" key="EN 300 706">European Telecommunications Standards Institute,
<titleref href="http://webapp.etsi.org/action%5COP/OP20030411/en_300706v010201o.pdf">Enhanced
Teletext Specification</titleref>. (See
<xspecref href="http://webapp.etsi.org/action%5COP/OP20030411/en_300706v010201o.pdf">http://webapp.etsi.org/action%5COP/OP20030411/en_300706v010201o.pdf</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="en300743" key="EN 300 743">European Telecommunications Standards Institute,
<titleref href="http://webapp.etsi.org/action%5COP/OP20021004/en_300743v010201o.pdf">Digital Video
Broadcasting (DVB); Subtitling Systems</titleref>. (See
<xspecref href="http://webapp.etsi.org/action%5COP/OP20021004/en_300743v010201o.pdf">http://webapp.etsi.org/action%5COP/OP20021004/en_300743v010201o.pdf</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="qtext" key="QText">Apple Computers, Inc.,
<titleref href="http://www.apple.com/quicktime/tools_tips/tutorials/texttracks.html">QuickTime Text</titleref>.
(See <loc href="http://www.apple.com/quicktime/tools_tips/tutorials/texttracks.html">http://www.apple.com/quicktime/tools_tips/tutorials/texttracks.html</loc>).
</bibl>
<bibl id="realtext" key="RealText">RealNetworks, Inc.,
<titleref href="http://www.realnetworks.com/resources/howto/realtext/index.html">RealText Markup</titleref>.
(See <loc href="http://www.realnetworks.com/resources/howto/realtext/index.html">http://www.realnetworks.com/resources/howto/realtext/index.html</loc>).
</bibl>
<bibl id="sami" key="SAMI">Microsoft Corporation,
<titleref href="http://www.msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/dnacc/html/atg_samiarticle.asp">SAMI &ndash;
Synchronized Accessible Media Interchange for Windows Media Player</titleref>. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/dnacc/html/atg_samiarticle.asp">http://www.msdn.microsoft.com/library/default.asp?url=/library/en-us/dnacc/html/atg_samiarticle.asp</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="smil20" key="SMIL 2.0">Jeff Ayars, Dick Bulterman, et al., Eds.,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/smil20/">Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language (SMIL 2.0)</titleref>,
W3C Recommendation. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/smil20/">http://www.w3.org/TR/smil20/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="tei" key="TEI">C. M. Sperberg-McQueen and Lou Burnard, Eds.,
<titleref href="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines2/index.html">TEI P4: Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</titleref>,
Text Encoding Initiative Consortium, Oxford, 2002.
(See <xspecref href="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines2/index.html">http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines2/index.html</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="xhtml1" key="XHTML 1.0">Steven Pemberton, et al., Eds.,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/">XHTML&trade; 1.0 Extensible Hypertext
Markup Language (Second Edition)</titleref>, W3C Recommendation.
(See <xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/">http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
<bibl id="xsl" key="XSL 1.0">Sharon Adler, Anders Berglund, et al., Eds.,
<titleref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xsl/">Extensible Stylesheet Language, Version 1.0</titleref>,
W3C Recommendation. (See
<xspecref href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xsl/">http://www.w3.org/TR/xsl/</xspecref>.)
</bibl>
</blist>
</inform-div1>
<inform-div1 id="acknowledgements">
<head>Acknowledgments</head>
<p>The editor acknowledges the members of the Timed Text Working
Group, the members of other W3C Working Groups, and industry experts
in other forums who have contributed directly or indirectly to the
process or content of creating this document.</p>
<p>The current and former members of the Timed Text Working Group are:
Glenn Adams, Extensible Formatting Systems, Inc. (chair);
Kees Blom, CWI;
Brad Botkin, WGBH;
Dick Bulterman, CWI;
Michael Dolan, Invited Expert;
Gerry Fields, WGBH;
Geoff Freed, WGBH;
Markus Gylling, DAISY Consortium;
Markku Hakkinen, Japanese Society for Rehabilitation of Persons with Disabilities;
Sean Hayes, Microsoft;
Erik Hodge, RealNetworks;
Masahiko Kaneko, Microsoft;
George Kerscher, DAISY Consortium;
David Kirby, BBC;
Thierry Michel, W3C (team contact);
Patrick Schmitz, Invited Expert;
and, Dave Singer, Apple Computer.
</p>
<p>The Timed Text Working Group has benefited in its work from the
participation and contributions of a number of people not currently
members of the Working Group, including in particular those named
below. Affiliations given are those current at the time of their work
with the WG.</p>
<p>
John Birch, Screen Subtitling Systems;
Bert Bos, W3C (chair, CSS WG);
Martin D&uuml;rst, W3C (leader, I18N Activity);
Al Gilman (chair, WAI Protocol and Formats WG);
Philipp Hoschka, W3C (leader, Interaction Domain);
Chris Lilley, W3C (chair, SVG WG).
</p>
</inform-div1>
</back>
</spec>
