<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<status id="status">
<p>
<emph>This section describes the status of this document at the
time of its publication. Other documents may supersede this document.
A list of current W3C publications and the latest revision of this
technical report can be found in the <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/TR/">W3C technical reports index</loc> at
http://www.w3.org/TR/.</emph>
</p>
<p>
This is the &draft.day;&nbsp;&draft.month;&nbsp;&draft.year; Candidate
Recommendation of the Timed Text (TT) Authoring Format
&versionOfTT;&nbsp;&ndash; Distribution Format Exchange Profile (DFXP).  W3C
publishes a Candidate Recommendation to indicate that the document is believed
to be stable and to encourage implementation by the developer community.  The
<loc href="http://www.w3.org/AudioVideo/TT/">Timed Text (TT) Working Group</loc>
expects to request that the Director advance this document to Proposed
Recommendation once the Working Group has, for each test in the <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/2006/DFXP/testsuite/Overview.html">DFXP 1.0 Test
Suite</loc>, demonstrated support by two interoperable
implementations.  The Working Group, working closely with the developer community,
expects to show these implementations by 16 February 2007. This estimate is based in
part on the preliminary <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/2006/DFXP/DFXP-implementation-result.html">DFXP
Interoperability Implementation Report</loc>.  The Working Group does not plan
to request to advance to Proposed Recommendation prior to 16 January 2007.
</p>
<p>
This is a W3C Candidate Recommendation. The second Last Call Working Draft for
this specification resulted in a number of Last Call comments which have all
been addressed by the working group; a list of all Last Call comments can be
found in the <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/2005/03/21/DFXP-2ND-LastCallResponses.html">Second Last Call
Comments List</loc>.  The list of changes made since the last public Working
Draft is available in <specref ref="change-history-lc2-to-cr"/>.
</p>
<p>
During the first Last Call period of this specification, there were <loc
href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-tt/2005Apr/0040.html">unsatisfied
comments</loc> that the working group was unable to resolve in a manner that satisfied
the commenter(s). The status of these comments has not changed during the second
Last Call period, as the working group continues to stand by its <loc
href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-tt/2005Oct/0000.html">original
responses</loc>. See also the <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/2005/03/21/DFXPLastCallResponses.html#Issue11">First
Last Call Disposition of Comments</loc> for a complete discussion.
</p>
<p>
The <emph>dynamic flow processing</emph> feature, as specified by
the <loc href="#style-attribute-dynamicFlow"><att>tts:dynamicFlow</att></loc>
styling attribute vocabulary, see
also <specref ref="dynamicFlowModel"/>, has been determined to be
<loc
href="http://www.w3.org/2005/10/Process-20051014/tr.html#at-risk-feature">at
risk</loc>, and is expected to be given the greatest scrutiny in the
implementation report.
</p>
<p>
Comments on this document should be sent to the email list <loc
href="mailto:public-tt@w3.org">public-tt@w3.org</loc>, which is the public
mailing list of Timed Text Working Group (<loc
href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-tt/">list archives</loc>).  To
subscribe, send an email to <loc
href="mailto:public-tt-request@w3.org">public-tt-request@w3.org</loc> with the
word <code>subscribe</code> in the subject line.
</p>
<p>
This document has been produced by the <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/AudioVideo/TT/">Timed Text (TT) Working Group</loc> as
part of the W3C <loc href="http://www.w3.org/AudioVideo/Activity">Synchronized
Multimedia Activity</loc>, following the procedures set out for the W3C <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Process/">Process</loc>.  The authors of this
document are listed in the header of this document.
</p>
<p> This document is governed by the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/TR/2002/NOTE-patent-practice-20020124">24 January 2002 CPP</loc> as amended by the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/05-pp-transition">W3C Patent Policy Transition Procedure</loc>. W3C maintains a <loc role="disclosure" href="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/Timed-text-Patent-statements.html">public list of any patent disclosures</loc> made in connection with the deliverables of the group; that page also includes instructions for disclosing a patent. An individual who has actual knowledge of a patent which the individual believes contains <loc href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/#def-essential">Essential Claim(s)</loc> must disclose the information in accordance with <loc href="http://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/#sec-Disclosure">section 6 of the W3C Patent Policy</loc>. </p>
<p>
Publication as a Candidate Recommendation does not imply endorsement by the W3C
Membership.  This is a draft document and may be updated, replaced or obsoleted
by other documents at any time. It is inappropriate to cite this document as
other than work in progress.
</p>
</status>
