<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>

<status id="status">

<p><emph>This section describes the status of this document at the
time of its publication. Other documents may supersede this
document. A list of current W3C publications and the latest revision
of this technical report can be found in the <loc
href="https://www.w3.org/TR/">W3C technical reports index</loc> at
https://www.w3.org/TR/.</emph></p>

<p>This is the Second Candidate Recommendation (CR2) of the Timed Text
Markup Language &versionOfTT; (TTML&versionOfTT;), and is intended to
be progressed to a W3C Recommendation. If you wish to make comments
regarding this document, please file an <loc
href="https://github.com/w3c/ttml2/issues">issue on GitHub</loc> or
send email to <loc
href="mailto:public-tt@w3.org">public-tt@w3.org</loc> (<loc
href="mailto:public-tt-request@w3.org?subject=subscribe">subscribe</loc>,
<loc
href="http://lists.w3.org/Archives/Public/public-tt/">archives</loc>)
with a subject line starting with <code>[ttml2]</code>. The deadline for
comments is 26 July 2018.</p>

<p>The W3C publishes
a Candidate Recommendation to indicate that the document is believed
to be stable and to encourage implementation by the developer
community. This Candidate Recommendation is expected to advance to
Proposed Recommendation no earlier than 9 August 2018.</p>

<p>For this specification to exit CR, the following criteria must be
met, as documented in the Working Group's <loc
href="https://www.w3.org/wiki/TTML/TTML2ImplementationReport">implementation
report</loc>. For each feature introduced in this specification:</p>

<olist>
  <item><p>At least two independent implementations must support the
  feature. If both transformation semantics and presentation semantics
  are defined for the feature, then at least one implementation must
  be a transformation processor and at least one implementation must
  be a presentation processor;</p></item>
  <item><p>At least one of those implementations must be a validating
  processor that successfully verifies valid or invalid use of the
  feature as applicable.</p></item>
</olist>

<p>The following features are at-risk, and may be dropped during the CR period:</p>

<ulist>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-animation-version-2">#animation-version-2</loc></p></item>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-border-radii">#border-radii</loc></p></item>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-bpd">#bpd</loc></p></item>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-display-inlineBlock">#display-inlineBlock</loc></p></item>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-extent-measure">#extent-measure</loc></p></item>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-font">#font</loc></p></item>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-fontSelectionStrategy-character">#fontSelectionStrategy-character</loc></p></item>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-ipd">#ipd</loc></p></item>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-lineShear">#lineShear</loc></p></item>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-region-implied-animation">#region-implied-animation</loc></p></item>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-rubyAlign-withBase">#rubyAlign-withBase</loc></p></item>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-shear">#shear</loc></p></item>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-textOrientation-sideways-LR">#textOrientation-sideways-LR</loc></p></item>
<item><p><loc href="#feature-validation">#validation</loc></p></item>
</ulist>

<p>The term “at-risk” is a W3C Process term-of-art, and does not
necessarily imply that the feature is in danger of being dropped or
delayed. It means that the Working Group believes the feature may have
difficulty being interoperably implemented in a timely manner, and
marking it as such allows the Working Group to drop the feature if
necessary when transitioning to the Proposed Recommendation stage
without having to publish a new Candidate Recommendation omitting the
feature.</p>

<p>A cumulative summary of all changes applied to this version since
the current (TTML1, 2nd Edition) Recommendation was published is
available at <loc href="ttml2-changes.html">Timed Text Markup Language
2 (TTML2) Change Summary</loc>.  An abbreviated list of changes
affecting language syntax can be found at
<specref ref="changes-from-ttml1-vocabulary"/>.</p>

<p>This document has been produced by the <loc
href="https://www.w3.org/AudioVideo/TT/">Timed Text (TT) Working
Group</loc> as part of the W3C <loc
href="http://www.w3.org/2008/WebVideo/">Video in the Web
Activity</loc>, following the procedures set out for the W3C <loc
href="https://www.w3.org/Consortium/Process/">Process</loc>.  The
authors of this document are listed in the header of this
document.</p>

<p>Publication as a Candidate Recommendation does not imply
endorsement by the W3C Membership. This is a draft document and may be
updated, replaced or obsoleted by other documents at any time. It is
inappropriate to cite this document as other than work in
progress.</p>


<p>This document was produced by a group operating under the <loc
href="https://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy/">W3C Patent
Policy</loc>.  W3C maintains a <loc role="disclosure"
href="https://www.w3.org/2004/01/pp-impl/34314/status#disclosures">public
list of any patent disclosures</loc> made in connection with the
deliverables of the group; that page also includes instructions for
disclosing a patent. An individual who has actual knowledge of a
patent which the individual believes contains <loc
href="https://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/#def-essential">Essential
Claim(s)</loc> must disclose the information in accordance with <loc
href="https://www.w3.org/Consortium/Patent-Policy-20040205/#sec-Disclosure">section
6 of the W3C Patent Policy</loc>.</p>

<p>This document is governed by the <loc id="w3c_process_revision"
href="https://www.w3.org/2018/Process-20180201/">1 February 2018 W3C
Process Document</loc>.</p>

</status>
